[Music]
yeah
okay it's recording
um so for for Joseph for Daniel for the
rest of the Institute who's uh following
along remotely uh or via YouTube um
welcome to the active inference
Institute uh we do a uh weekly textbook
group readings uh twice on Thursdays
once in the morning once in the evening
uh if you're if you're roughly in the
Western Hemisphere and um yeah so so
today we're going over chapter 7 in
cohort 7 um and we'll be talking about
essentially the Exemplar discret State
space models and active inference that
would be hidden Markov models and uh
partially observable decision- making
processes we have a nice Taz example
which is pretty classic in in the field
as well as in kind of Behavioral and and
and and Neuroscience and neur
neuroimaging studies in general and uh
again we're in the second half or part
two of the book which is highly
dedicated to to constructing uh
essentially active inference models as
opposed to part one which is much more
focused on Theory and and definitions um
and so it's for anyone who's interested
in computational modeling whether it be
doing it themselves or getting a clearer
grasp of kind of what are these
computational models or cognitive models
that we're putting together in order to
say collaborate with a uh Team of of
people who do do comp cognitive modeling
then it it's very worthwhile to spend
time with the second half of the book
and then furthermore there are just
there are many discreet State spaces in
in in a very general sense in a in a
physical sense and a kind of decision
making and and and and human belief
sense it's referring to scenarios where
essentially if we think about it in data
it's sort of like U categories it's
thinking about binaries uh it's not so
much thinking about uh fully continuous
number series such as a range over one
through a million where we could have so
many different uh different values
including with the decimal points um
potentially an infinite number of values
instead we're looking at
say RGB color scales on old televisions
so red blue green um we could have a
distribution between the three of them
in the sense of how much red how much
blue and how much green uh but
nonetheless it's it's a kind of um
discreet uh categorization process so um
yeah I normally I give a rather long uh
kind of chapter summary but I'm happy to
just kind of open up the floor if uh
Joseph you have any particular questions
or things you'd like to discuss
here um I I would like to hear your
summary um I also do have some questions
um I haven't fully been able to
understand um for example figure 72 so
it if we could like I I I guess I just
don't understand what plotted and and
where the lines are coming from but
um yeah I I'm I'm very interested in and
trying to build these models and
understand how to build them and um and
so this seems like a really critical
chapter for for
me yeah yeah no that's great um yeah
figure 72 which I I personally have not
spent a lot of time with recently
so coming back to it is rather
interesting yeah so the the this is
where the chapter it essentially opens
with hidden marov models uh before we
jump up
to uh partially observable marov
decision-making processes so it's like
we have um I believe my is my screen
still being shared appropriately or can
you not see anything uh no I don't see
your screen okay got it thanks for that
just realized I doing a a little bit of
uh display
gymnastics um that should have done it
so this is and a quick reference this is
the Koda for the textbook group and so
we have this available to all members
and we have um not just a overview of
the textbook group and you know
dedicated uh meetings and and time
availability and and all those sorts of
things for the separate cohorts we also
have a pretty good breakdown of the
active inference textbook especially
since it became open
source so um so yeah figure 71 I know
it's not the one you referenced but just
to make sure we're like familiar with it
enough this is essentially hidden Markov
model and so understanding kind of the
core Dynamics here uh we ult ultimately
only have three different components in
this model so we have D our prior over
initial States it's kind of like what
are our beliefs about States whenever we
come into a situation as it were um and
then from there uh that gets linked to
uh observations that we receive right
and the relationship between what we
believe and sort of what we see is
linked through this this likelihood
Matrix a so it's represented as is kind
of this broad categorical probability
distribution that is conditional uh
observations given our beliefs s or in
States s and then there's also a
temporal Dynamic over time right so we
have the B Matrix which is kind of our
beliefs about how transitions change
from one to another so that's why we
have this sort of State at T minus one
to State at T to State t+ one so it's
this this temporal Dynamic playing out
over discrete time steps um and so from
there you can move to
7.2 a little bit of context so this is
this is an example that relates to the
idea I believe it's of of someone who's
playing uh an instrument and they're
trying to actually play a song in accord
with the the script the sheet music that
they're reading and so we can quickly
imagine scenario where there's someone
who is still learning how to play this
is practice for them even if it's
someone who's very skilled there maybe
learning a new piece for like I don't
know an orchestra performance they'll be
doing soon um and so there's all kinds
of room for error right and to to
accidentally hit the wrong notes at the
wrong time maybe you're still on beat
but uh but you know you hit an a rather
than an A flat and so that's sort of
what this this example is about is being
able to to use the Dynamics of a hidden
Markov model including What notes play
over time and then also what does the
musician believe the note should be
versus what we we actually hear um right
and so so by being able to like hear and
it's obviously a very kind of abstracted
example there's a lot more to it there
we're not saying anything about what the
sheet music looks like but here we're
just simplifying it to saying the
musician has a belief about what the
note should be versus what they actually
observe that they're they're playing
so with this figure 7.2 I think the the
quickest way of kind of getting at what
the authors of the textbook are trying
to demonstrate for us is sort of an
illustrative example is this upper right
this is like beliefs about hidden States
so the agent believes that the first
note uh in terms of over time time
should in fact be the first note as in
it's in row one so that this row is like
its own set of notes row two is the uh
yet another note so it could be read as
like the top row is a the second row is
a sharp the next row is B the next row
is c not to confuse anyone who's not
familiar with scales but we there is no
B Sharp essentially unless you're
concerned with Naturals and all that so
um so each row is its own note and then
I here it's kind of like the the
musician believes based on the sheet
music that they should start with the
first note a and then move to a sharp
move to B move to C and then go back to
a for the fifth note so they're just
kind of descending a chromatic scale
before they get back to a again that's
what they believe should happen
meanwhile with our O's or
observations what really happens is that
we get an A we get an A sharp and then
rather than getting the expected B is
here we the the actual observation is
that they realize oh no they hit the
same note twice in a row which is not
correct but by the fourth time step they
get back to what the note should be and
then here uh at time step five they also
hit the correct note so kind of what's
What's Happening Here is that there is
at at S3 we would say that this is
prediction error right and so with
whenever the agent infers their
posteriors over hidden States here
they're so conditioned to believe that
it should be the right note that that
they kind of shaded this in as if it's
correct but there's this grayness here
it's very it's so light but but the
essentially the idea is you know this is
the note that should have happened their
prior their observation however gives
them evidence that it's actually this
Grace space this is maybe actually the
that they heard um or that they believe
really happened so there there are
aspects of this that can seem kind of
counterintuitive but really just being
able to grasp that the upper right are
their beliefs about States the lower uh
the lower right is the observations they
actually receive and then a good
reminder is you know in a discreet State
space setting it's like oh we're not
looking
at you know the interim between a and a
sharp you know some kind of microtonal
situation we're just looking at uh we're
assuming there's a and then there's a
sharp and then there's B and there's C
and ultimately they're that's the
Western scale of 12 notes um in the way
that I'm describing the examples so now
these these graphs on the left are a
little more complex um and it will be
good to spend a little bit of time with
them I'll first just like read what it
says in the textbook so so we'll go with
lower left we're looking at negative
free energy gradients or prediction
errors the rate of change of the beliefs
in the upper left
plot is determined by the value of these
errors at each time step and so what
we're seeing these are negative free
energy gradients in terms of active
inference we're wanting to minimize
prediction error we're wanting to
minimize variational free energy so if
these are
actually negative gradients then that
means that at each time step we should
actually want these to be rather large
um if they're negative and so the the
smaller they are you know it's kind of
like saying that it's sort of the the
worser scenario and then that seems to
kind of constrain the agent's ability to
to be confident or or or kind of
understand the the situation so um see
and then
upper left beliefs posterior
probabilities about each note in the
sequence of each time step yeah so the
these are the posterior probabilities
it's kind of like their ability to
understand a particular note here of
what it should have been has gone down
right so there's a kind of constraint
there that's been applied and then once
they start to hear the correct notes
again their confidence kind of kind of
increases I will be honest these kinds
of these two graphs on the left they're
much more rarely used today in active
inference like these specific types it
might be because of this sort of kind
kind of uh counterintuitive nature
because more often than not we actually
are looking at you know the inverse of
the situation so we're looking at
positive free energy and so actually
this would look quite bad it would look
like step three is actually you know a
rather good thing in terms of minimizing
uncertainty and it's the other way
around but I I think that the authors
who who compose this are really trying
to get at a particular kind of Point by
representing it this
way I I think I'm still maybe a little
lost
about so um you said that just focusing
on this top left um the the y axis you
said is probability so okay so I I get
that and what are all the different
Minds um are
these
different
trials
[Music]
or
yeah yeah it's
quite yeah one of the things I'm really
wanting to understand better is
um uh how the agent actually is learning
and and maybe that comes later on this
is after this example but
um where do do we adjust the weights of
this of the the in these matrices um
according to the result we get from our
minimization step oh yeah no that that's
an excellent question very relevant so
so in this example they don't actually
apply learning at all so this is
essentially like a static model yeah um
and I think they're just using it to try
and kind of get at the more inference
level Dynamics as opposed to learning
and so I I know that this is you know
this is pretty familiar terminology for
folks who do other forms of kind of
computational modeling data science deep
learning uh I heard you say that you
know referring to it is adjusting the
weights all of that is very relevant
here but so so for this particular model
yeah there is no learning what would
what could happen is
that refer to this
again um this what typically what an
agent learns are these kind of
probability
distributions over time and so D you
know the your your prior beliefs in the
basian sense those could be updated so
you could the agent could effectively
learn its D matric um a could be learned
B could be learned actually any of its
parameters including c and e which C is
just a prior over observations e is a
prior over over policies or actions um
so so that way you know that's what's
missing from this and it's also missing
from this because we have no policy
inference right so the hmm is kind of
like can be viewed as a
truncated version of the pmdp which is
exactly equivalent until we get to hear
it this connection to to Pi or
representing policies or action and so
so an hmm is kind of like perception and
no action uh partially observable markup
decision-making process is perception
and here we have the connection to
actions that it can take so we get these
these kind of relationships we suddenly
State transitions the B
Matrix recall earlier 7.2
the B is simply what is the next state
going to be given the current state
whereas here we now
have yeah we now have what is the next
state going to be given the current
state as well as an action I take so
that is sort of the kind of the the
agency so to speak that this this agent
has um and its ability to kind of infer
which actions to take and furthermore um
e the prior over policies I mean that so
that can be learned that gets
Incorporated C preferences prior over
observations there're those are more
often left static so those are more
often left static in the sense that they
become a kind of attracting point for
particular
observations uh in that case that kind
of supplies the agent with a sort of
goal um and kind of like it's seeking
out particular observations that it it
it prefers or EXP specs um in the sort
of theoretical literature the idea is
that it relates to the notion of
homeostasis so I prefer to observe my
blood oxygen level being at a certain
point or I prefer to not observe my
stomach growling because usually it's a
sign that I'm hungry and I need to do
something about that which in a that
context it would that that c would then
inform what I should do via the B Matrix
of oh my stomach growling must mean I'm
hungry I know that if I eat food I will
S I will no longer be hungry at the next
time step so to speak um so so again any
of these can be learned and I know that
there's a nice figure that kind of HS at
the point of this but I don't want to
get us too Lost In The Weeds
um thing Hybrid
models the essentially what happens is
that we end up with this kind of hyper
parameterization of all of those model
components okay I'll stop I'll stop
scrolling around because it might be
that we missed that one still relatively
new um so you would have like a prior on
D which itself is in the discrete State
space setting so it would be it would
just be like a kind of so it' be a de
lay distribution so so it would be like
a categorical distribution but the
values can in fact exceed one they don't
have to sum to one you could almost
think of it as a kind of like dear L
count system where it's like oh I I you
know I have my D Matrix but then I've
also experienced like more of this state
in many more time steps so it implies
that there that an agent actually has a
history of states and a history of
observations that it's kind of
accumulated and then that ACC is a kind
of hyperparameter on these matrices
which then proceeds to modulate their
values and then learning them itself
will involve free energy minimization I
it's just applying another free energy
minimization rule um and so and so like
minimizing free energy is sort of the
global uh functional or optimization
problem here for just about everything
like State like inferring States URS by
minimizing variational free energy
inferring
policies heavily relies on uh minimizing
expected free energy which uh earlier on
in the textbook I think it's somewhere
in the realm of chapters 2 through 4 uh
there's kind of a broad
breakdown about those terms so feel we
should be able to find those we have the
equations as
well yeah
great so something we'll notice very
quickly between f and g f is going to be
for Again State inference which ends up
being treated as a separate process
related but if if you were to code this
like if you were to write this in code
you would actually write like separate
Logics and even executions of State
inference versus policy inference State
inference will involve Min minimizing F
which without getting too lost in the
various ways we can break this down we
could look at it as complexity minus
accuracy which is the sort of classic
you know machine learning imperative of
how do you create a model that can both
be generalizable and not excessively
complex and overfit um but we need it to
be accurate so we don't want it to
heavily underfit either so the the
complexity term there is just what is
the K Divergence between your posteriors
what you think now versus is your prior
what you thought before and then you
want
to also keep accuracy high so we want to
be able to find the expected value of
the log of essentially observations
given X so so all this is to say each
one of these terms depending on what the
sign is in front of them um we'll we'll
want to either maximize or minimize so
we'll want to maximize accuracy right
because it has a negative sign in front
of it vice versa for complexity we
actually want to minimize that because
at the end of the day we come back to F
we're just trying to minimize that
um similarly for G but the interesting
thing with G is that whenever we look at
just the Top
Line Information Gain and pragmatic
value we notice that there are negative
signs in front of both of them and we're
trying to minimize G so we actually here
want to maximize Information Gain
meaning the the the expected value of
the kale Divergence between sort of what
you your posteriors what you what you
think
now conditioned on what you've seen and
what you've done and the the Divergence
between that and just what you think now
versus uh are conditioned on what you
have done so this is kind of like saying
oh now that I have actually observed the
outcomes of what I have done in what I
believe Now versus simply just relying
on you know sort of what I've done it it
it kind of prioritizes this idea of oh I
need to collect more observations and I
actually want those observations to be
quite different from what I you I'm used
to seeing before what I'm so used to
that I can practically sort of
marginalize them out right so that
that's sort of the exploratory Behavior
we see in active inference and
furthermore just the fact that we have
this functional that actually allows for
both exploratory behavior and pragmatic
value which is simply your observations
conditioned on C so like I mentioned
earlier C it's often used for defining
like goals that the agent has it's kind
of like the what you expect is what you
want which is what will help you
maintain homeostasis or it's what will
help you achieve that goal you have in
the far future or however you want to
look at it um or go in the mediate
future and so you want your observations
to essentially like you you you want
what you see to actually be accurate
versus like your priors over
observations right so that that's that's
kind of I don't know if you're familiar
with reinforcement learning but anything
like uh Epsilon greedy Behavior or
having to like Define manual rules such
as like oh you should always exploit
with a probability of 0.9 and you know
10% of the time just do something random
and see see what happens instead instead
this is what it defines exploratory
behavior is directly implicated in
Computing minimizing expected free
energy so the that's the claim in the
textbook that these sort of naturally
balance out which
is not a sentence that really really
should be said that way in the sense of
you could still have a scenario where a
policy is evaluated such that it might
not have any information gain at all
it's just the fact that both are
computed and so there is no manual
definition here we're just relying upon
minimizing G and these particular
equations I might have gone much more
deeply into that and I I hope I didn't
miss no I I really appreciated that I
liked your explanation about um the the
the meaning of those different
distributions that you're me measuring
the kale
Divergence um that that was very helpful
actually uh especially when you were
talking about the uh Information Gain
and the fact that you know one is
conditioned on why hat or why Tilda and
one is
not um I I had I just sort of not
connected those dots before
so
yeah yeah no problem at all I me can you
say again I think you said it already
but can you say again the difference
between p and Q is this related to the
world model versus the uh agents model
like the truth the true World versus the
agents what's in the agent's head or is
it something else yeah sure no good
question so um if we were to kind of use
the phrase is it just in the agent's
head or the world it's all of this would
be in the agent's head okay so yeah yeah
so and then uh in the sense that like
this is the agent's beliefs about States
this is the these are the this is kind
of the breakdown of the overall rule of
computing free energy Over States so
States as and my my beliefs about the
world and then G will be used for
inferring what policy should I use so
that's as opposed to State inference
it's policy inference right okay so the
and and and all of it is in the in the
agent's head as it were and then for Q
and P so Q is always used they they
always use that to denote posteriors so
this is sort of like what what do I
think after a given instance vers you
know and versus what did I think before
right so there's this kind of model
inversion process that that that happens
where where we compute
F by sort of fig sorry about
this figuring out our posteriors
figuring out our relative to our priors
and that's what allows us to kind of
score the final like what is our final
belief now that that we have all of that
and we have now minimized the free
energy right so just basically basically
employing basian inference but in the
context of a fuller functional equation
yeah yeah so so you know there are a lot
of interesting ways that the these terms
get broken down and I know that like for
for a lot of folks who get involved with
the Institute and their Learners uh
especially those who are not terribly uh
you know comfortable with math or or
probability Theory it's sort of like
these things can be very intimidating
right to just like quickly see like you
know let us tell you all at once all
these different ways you can break down
G whenever you're still trying to learn
what this little C is over here and what
how what that means relative to anything
else right and what's the Tilda about
right so and I'll also I guess I'll
mention that the Tilda is U so G what
you're doing here with G and the the
whole G over pi is you're you're
inferring your beliefs about each policy
you have available over some inference
Horizon which is why we call it expected
free energy it's that it it also is
variational in the sense of like
there're we're relying on different
kinds of you know approximate methods
variational methods here but the the the
expected part is emphasize because if if
if I notice I'm hungry and I'm trying to
decide what to do it's like well if I
need to if I decide one policy I have is
that I need food there's going to be a
series of steps that I'm going to need
to take do I have food in my fridge do
is it at the store if it's at you know
if I decide going to the store is what I
want to do then like what are the
intermediary steps of what I need to do
from between now and then um surely I
don't think about every single thing
like the entire process of what it will
be like for me to walk down my apartment
complex's hallway but more discreetly
know that I will need to say stand up
and then I'll need to leave my apartment
and then I'll need to travel or take
transit or otherwise to the store and so
on so so it's kind of like the Tilda is
just acknowledging that this is a
sequence so what what are the kind of
expectations I have over what will
happen if I follow a particular policy
and and how I think it'll occur so um
which is why we also don't see the Tilda
up here because this is more about
momentto moment inference which again
relates back to earlier the point about
learning right because it that's that's
an important distinction between the two
and active inference is uh State
inference is just about you know in real
time you know you think about again the
the musician playing notes in real time
and and it's very directly related to
their ability to hear the note that
they're playing versus what they think
it is um so that's that's one way of
kind of just more conceptually
conceiving of uh of these things
so okay and and so I guess um especially
with G it seems to me that the reason
you would choose one breakdown over the
other maybe with not just G but all of
them but um is because you're you're
trying to figure out what's actually
computable like based on the Computing
resources you
have maybe it's a lot easier to compute
um that fourth line there with the
expected energy and entropy and the
other
options in terms of uh what's actually
solvable
um that that's possible I mean it's
never made very EXP it why we have all
of these different breakdowns the The
crucial thing is that like the way the
math plays out it's necessarily the case
that this first line like one version of
G is Information Gain minus pragmatic
negative Information Gain minus
pragmatic values G it's necessarily
going to be equivalent to the value here
um given the the equation right and so
it's sort of
like now another sort of tricky thing is
that the this is sort of U they will be
less than or equal to these other terms
so the this allows for almost I don't
want to get too abstract and mix things
together but it's almost like this is an
additional like this is the the the
lower uh excuse me the upper bound of
the upper bound on like expected future
surprisal right it's because we already
know that um f from definitions of
surprise
like f is just an upper bound ons
surprise that that works out
mathematically and so it's kind of like
saying well these are the upper bounds
on surprise expected in the future and
these are kind of the upper bound to the
upper bound because of this sneaky uh
less than or equal to sign here right um
so so another thing is that it's sort of
like the another aspect of this beyond
that is uh the authors try to supply
their own definitions of the different
ways of breaking these down um and so
expected free energy in just about
every as broad generalization but I
would I genuinely think maybe 80% to 90%
of all literature you read in active
inference most people are just going to
focus on describing it this way
information gained pragmatic value
because it comes off as the most
intuitive and it's also the most
interesting in terms of viewing things
uh in like explore exploit paradigms
it's just this is the clearest way of
kind of um kind of expressing that and
so it's it's just intuitive like oh yes
I want more information that actually
increases like what what I thought
before versus what I know now it's
almost like I'm seeking out I hesitate
to use the word learning because of it's
It's technical connotation here but sort
of like I want to look learn more or I
want to find more you know it's a sort
of a someone who wants to have fun doing
something new for the sake of it you
know I sort of think about that as a
more colloquial way and then pragmatic
Valu is just you know is what I'm seeing
or what I expect to see is it going to
be aligned with my prior so so is what I
is this particular action this
particular policy I'm evaluating like
going to the store to get food is that
going to help
me achieve observations that match what
I want which is attaining food and kind
of watching and myself eat it and then
watching my stomach no longer growl is a
kind of odd way of saying it but it it's
closer to the the the ideal of of how it
would work yeah um I I think part of the
the break the breakdowns here is just
sort of it's taking into account so like
with expected ambiguity and these other
terms uh some of them additionally get
introduced in in chapter 7 as well um
posterior predictive entropy those kinds
of terms it's kind of like just saying
like oh it's it's sort of like this this
idea that you know there's a lot of
other dynamics of how we could view
these playing now so expected ambiguity
is like um oh that that for example is
sort of what is the entropy of what I
expect to see versus what I expect will
be going on so um you know if if if I
expect that the it will be light
outside because I believe it's daytime
and I expect to see that it's dark
outside as I believe that it is uh
nighttime then it's sort of like we have
this nice one toone discreet mapping
it's light out it must be day it's uh
dark out it must be night um however if
uh if we
if we
expect more of a one to mini mapping
such as uh oh it's light outside it
could be day or there or excuse me it's
dark outside it could be night or it
could be a solar eclipse right now right
and I'm just not sure which I didn't pay
attention to the news I don't know like
what's going on right so um that's
suddenly where you get more of a one to
mini mapping between like what could
this particular observation mean um and
here it's a it's a positive value so
we'd actually want to like minimize that
kind of that that entropy of that
situation thus expected
ambiguity um and then risk over outcomes
so these risk terms that get related to
because there are a lot of people who go
into this field not just because they're
interested in seeing Neuroscience but
they might be interested in other fields
I I myself have a a background in um I
did my uh Masters At You Chicago and
this very broad social sciences program
that's part of what part of what brought
me here uh including an interest in
economics so looking at risk so this is
like your posteriors versus your priors
like what what do you believe right now
about what you would expect to see
versus versus Pi versus like what what
do you believe after right so what what
do I expect to kind of see from what I
do versus what I I I'm used to sort of
um and finding the K Divergence between
those right and you want to minimize
that which is which is a little
different so it's just there's so many
ways to break it down and so many
different ways to attempt to put into
words why these equations work the way
they do that's sort of the the trick
isn't it of not just active inference
but sort of cognitive and computational
modeling in general like well if we have
real data and we have real approximate
methods of mapping things like beliefs
and actions and inference learning
processes what how do we put into
natural language what any of those
things
mean so it's a I think it's a fair
attempt and I I personally like many
other people kind of prefer this top one
but it is interesting breaking the rest
down and then it's it's kind of like the
further you go down the line here we get
closer and closer
to theoretical physics which is yet
another kind of partner field of active
inference and a lot of Carl friston the
other
folks's um research right so just having
energy terms
that yeah my my background is in physics
and I think that's a large part of why
this um appealed to me as
a I'm I'm working on a robotics company
so um that's how I came into this and
found it and and why I think attracted
me was the analogy to physics and
um I'm hoping to figure out some ways to
reduce the amount of data that it
requires to uh for an agent to learn a
task or to decide to do a set a sequence
of motions or something
yeah no absolutely I mean it's uh I
don't know if you skipped ahead to
um chapter 10 in this textbook at any
point but I think they spent some time
on on Robotics and and you know the the
the more theoretical aspects of like
cybernetic processes and sort of
feedback loop operations but then like
suddenly with active inference In This
Very broad interdisciplinary aspect it's
sort of like like because it can go so
many ways it because it comes out of
Neuroscience I mean one way one kind of
funny takeaway and maybe it's not funny
but I I I think it's kind of fun is uh
like a lot of this relates to the brain
and inference processes as well as
looking at Behavior like the tze example
that we get in his textbook so uh you
know like a similarly to actually having
a real mouse in a lab but then if
computational Psychiatry plays into this
a lot and it's actually like it's a
growing field and many people are trying
to cognitively model and I'm working
with a research group here as well uh
but we're working on a on creating an
active infer inference model of PTSD
actually and uh sort of what are the
behavioral Dynamics there and and sort
of the belief Dynamics and can you find
a a generalizable but still a
approximate um sort of model of these
these Dynamics in relation to
neurobiology and then in future like
being able to kind of fit that model to
real empirical data that could be
collected from you know willing
participants uh who have
PTSD um and and all this is to say the
reason why I'm kind of going on about it
despite the fact that you we start with
robotics is that it kind of in an
interesting it's almost like like is a
bad machine learning model or
reinforcement learning model like if
it's bad should we view that as a kind
of like like a pathology like can we
View suboptimal Behavior as sort of
something like pathological Behavior so
I I just think that's a that's a
fascinating kind of take and i' I've
talked to a few people who are more
focused on sort of sort of optimizing
models rather than you know they're not
worried about attending to human beings
and modeling that they're wanting to
create very efficient you know kind of
engineering based you know tools and and
and and so on U right and we've always
had interesting conversations about that
because because an active inference it's
like there's a term that's used
sometimes
um the term is a h hyper precise priors
and so that that would kind of be like a
scenario where to
bring it back a little bit it it could
be for example a situation
where skip it because it's
fig so like imagine an agent you know
imagine our musician example again we
don't have even have to worry about
policies just yet um imagine this agent
like had a very precise hyper parameter
like on their a like a very strong prior
for their a matrix and for some reason
they're just learning it at either an
incredibly slow rate or not at all um
and say the a matrix was really biased
so like with the with the this example
like say the agent was heavily biased to
assuming that like if their like their
these beliefs are necessarily like one
to one with with these to where even
this kind of light gray space didn't
appear so to speak it's like they
wouldn't track the prediction error
because they believe in the basian sense
so strongly that this is in fact how
things work you know perceptually given
that the hmm is just like a perceptual
model then it's kind of like saying like
oh that's you know it it in in robotics
that I mean that would be awful that
means it's not able to like read the
data streams in a way that allows it to
make any kind of like flexible
adjustable inferences instead it's it's
going to just assume whatever it sees
regardless of what it is just reconfirms
like its beliefs about you know what's
going on and If This Were a PDP then
also what it should do in response to
the data stream is receiving but uh
simultaneously the pathology bit is sort
of like oh that what for a musician that
would mean that they believe they're
really good at music all the time right
because they're they're sorely convinced
that their beliefs about what should be
heard or what should be played or what's
going on uh necessarily match the
incoming data stream and so the incoming
data stream will just kind of like it
won't the variations in it won't really
matter it's like there will still be it
won't even hear that they made a mistake
essentially they'll they'll believe that
it's right exactly and so not to you
know not to sound in you know
insensitive or or phrase this wrongly
but it's I mean if you start thinking
about things like schizophrenia or
psychosis where something in reality is
not going on at all but the person
believes it is it's like in a certain
way it's they're they're perceiving
reality in a way that's heavily biased
by these kind of priors that they're
coming to the situation with right so
you're sort of stuck in that uh if so
long as the your your inference process
is kind of you know kind of path
pathological in that way so um so yeah
it's I mean with robotics I'm not that's
not my my key field as it were so I
can't say too much other than anytime
I've skimmed it there's always
something being something interested
being said and that you know with a lot
of these models in various areas um
they're highly performative including in
When comparing them let's say to
reinforcement learning right because
it's another way of looking at active
inference especially especially pdps or
any any model that is actually augmented
with the capacity for Action we're
effectively just looking at okay here's
an agent who receives
observations and infers an action it
should take um if we just look at it as
a mark of decision making process like
remove the partially observable part
then it would just kind of be like they
are it's as if they already know what
the state is they observe a state it's
sort of more one to one we don't have
this
extra observation versus States
part right but but but nonetheless I
mean this is still the canonical bit
because I mean this is as far as kind of
the
Neuroscience Go I mean we're always in a
partially observable environment right
so we we don't always know what an
observation means and what we haven't
even said anything about like you know
the possibility that the sensory
receptor itself is bad whether it be you
know a person who's nearsight and so
anything far away is just very hard to
see or it be um you know a robot that
has a a receptor that is just like not
functioning correctly or um an EEG
headset that like you know someone left
the ground uh you know they didn't set
that up right and so it it it sees
really high amplitudes not because of
the person's neural activity it's
because it's getting like
supercharged um so in a inaccurate way
so that's sort of the part partially
observable bit um they do I mean anytime
I look at model comparisons it's just
you know people do very regularly
Benchmark um yeah they they regularly
Benchmark these models against
reinforcement learning models um
usually again and again you know
Furnishing an inherent balance of
exploration
and exploitation like so so a lot of
people point that out that they just
find a lot more sort of credibility in
thetion of like oh these agents because
of
G uh they're sort of
naturally internally you know
architecturally incentivized to seek out
more information and nonetheless like
once they're affirmed that they have
enough information
they are over time more than likely
going to become like oh no I've seen
that before so that they kind of know
not to go necessarily in that direction
however it's over a policy Horizon so
maybe that policy Horizon is five steps
in the future or in a continuous State
space it could be you know a minute into
the future uh and what they expect to
kind of see over along the way um you
know so so even if they think they've
explored a space well they might not
necessarily know the full sequence of
transitions that'll happen over time so
it's it's very likely that they'll be
able to depending on your setup
continuously find ways of like getting
Information Gain out of a situation
Computing that like incorporating that
into their decisionmaking but once they
become much more reaffirmed that they've
explored
enough then they start to you I'm I'm
speaking from from
experience sorry oh in Montery
Bay I'm not sure he's talking to us no
uh here you go um so
uh yeah I that kind of interrupted my
sorry train of thought but it's just to
get to the point it's like very often
the not I I think that t- example and
spending just like an extra not a long
time but just like a minute or two um
because I know with robotics you're
usually looking at continuous streams
right I mean maybe there's a I mean go
sorry go ahead yeah I was I was just
going to say yes um what I would love to
be able to do is take a six degree of
Freedom robot arm and output the six
joint
variables uh that are continuous you
know and U between some limits and um
that would all be given some sensory
input and then beliefs about what that
sensory input indicates about current
state yeah no it's incredibly relevant
to a lot of the work that is done here
and it's sort of you know one way that
they break down if you if you've looked
at the book and and become more familiar
with the notion of like an observation
modality which is you know a very common
sensical thing if you get rid of the
jargon it's just sort of like you know I
can see things things versus feel things
versus taste things like there there are
different ways that I can receive
information and and so they tend to
break those up into three different
categories and so there's um
exteroceptive which would be like
information I receive from the outside
which includes all the things I said
earlier that it's sort of common five
senses of like I can see and touch and
feel things interoceptive would be like
internal bodily signals um that are
coming like sort of from within that I'm
not necessarily feeling them in the in
the typical sense of like my skin is in
you know sort of dermal aspects um and
then there's proprioceptive and that
that's if you come across that
term Sorry by the way I don't mean to
sound kind of sending if you already are
familiar with it no this is great thank
you cool definitely yeah so so
proprioceptive I'm just trying to find
it quick and we might have to wrap up
then is uh
oh I know it's in
here um somewhere there's there's they
have a nice sort of visual description
of like the idea of
like that ah proprioceptive afer so this
is you know this is still related to
more like the brain but
proprioception you know has much more to
do with like movement and kind of
reactive systems so so there could be
like a reflex arc sort of logic for
example
um that that might be of interest to you
if you want a model that's kind of a
little bit more complex or sort of sort
of Savvy with with putting together the
architecture in regards to active
inference there's no necessity of it
though and I think you'll you'll you
might especially find chapter8
interesting which is going to explicitly
go over continuous models it of course
is different because of the continuous
Spa like time and continuous State space
sort of setup um but then in that case
we're looking at more like kind of these
attracting points or or here this is uh
this is rather complex but this is a
Lawrence you know chaotic system and
sort of like different kinds of Dynamics
and viewing them in different ways and
viewing how you know like I mentioned
with the discrete State space setting
there's C which is sort of defining your
goals or your expected observations you
want um the the sort of equivalent of
that in continuous State space models
you could view that as uh sort of like
an attracting point or or a distribution
of attracting points or an attracting
distribution uh over a continuous space
and just modeling it like that um you'll
also it it relies a lot more on sort of
tailor series approximations there's
this notion he calls refers to it as the
uh generalized coordinates of motion so
it's sort of like the through these more
sort of working more with more directly
and explicitly with derivatives um over
time so um yeah it's yeah I realized
that that actually kind of shot by the
time um but uh thanks for this uh
opportunity to get into uh to sort of
the deeper theoretics and and and really
honing in on some of these equations uh
you know some yeah it's sometimes folks
with the here I'll
I'll pause um also thanks for bearing
with the this is my first time ever when
I'm doing this purely solo
so yeah um so I'll go ahead and stop
recording and thank you everyone and see
you at the next see you at the next one